A Guide to the Roller Family Papers 1828-1974
Virginia Historical Society
- Margaret Etta (Cabell) Matthews (1876-1969) papers, 1888-1954
  - Correspondence, 1888-1954, 36 items (Folder 28)
    Mimmie [?]
    Bentley, Sallie P.
    Cabell, Elsie Francis
    Donald, Josephine
    Seddon, Ella B. C.
    Shipman, Hattie
    [Theirdon], Catherine R.
    Witt, Annie
  - Miscellaneous materials, 3 items (Box 28)
    Include accounts, 1903, and an essay on "Fires," 1888.
- Royal Eubank Cabell (1878-1950) correspondence, 1897-1912, 7 items (Box 28)
  Chiefly with niece Lucy Cabell Roller of Harrisonburg, Va., while Cabell was travelling to the West Coast. Of particular interest is a letter of Mrs. Thomas B. Land enclosing an advertisement for the Woodstock School, Mathews co., Va., 1899.
  Fox, L. A.
  Lane, Thomas B. (Mrs.)
- Somers Eubank Cabell (1885-1919) school materials, 1903-1904, 4 items (Box 28)
  Include monthly reports from Virginia Polytechnic Institute.
- Frances Lewis (Roller) Grattan correspondence, 1897-1959, 20 items (Box 29)
  Correspondence of Frances Lewis "Lewie" (Roller) Grattan, primarily with her half-sister, Elizabeth Henry (Roller) Bottimore, and other female relatives concerning family affairs. Included are two love-letters from P. Howell Lightfoot of Petersburg, Va., 1901.
  "Whistles" (otherwise unidentified)
  Margaret [?]
  Baker, Miriam Lee
  Lightfoot, P. Howell
  Mayo, Louisa R.
  Merryman, Margaret Stuart (Roller) Cannady Ogilvie
  Penets, S. V.
- Margaret Stuart (Roller) Cannady Ogilvie Merryman papers, 1899-1947
  - Correspondence, 1899-1947, 21 items (Box 29)
    Scattered correspondence of Margaret Stuart "Marco" (Roller) Cannady Ogilvie Merryman, including letters to her half-sisters, Elizabeth Henry (Roller) Bottimore, Anne Woolston (Roller) Pyle, and Lucy Cabell Roller (concerning the disposal of John Edwin Roller's library).
    Mason, H. Norton
    Pyle, Anne Woolston (Roller) See Bottimore, Elizabeth Henry (Roller)
  - School materials, 1897-1898, 5 items (Box 29)
    From Woman's College, Frederick, Md. [now Hood College] and Virginia Female Institute, Staunton, Va., including programs, grade reports, accounts, and an essay.
- Lucy Cabell Roller (1899-1949) papers, 1899-1947
  - Correspondence, 1899-1947, 69 items (Box 29)
    Correspondence of "Lucy Cabell" Roller (of Harrisonburg and Richmond, Va., and while attending Randolph-Macon Women's College, Lynchburg, Va.) with her sisters, Elizabeth Henry (Roller) Bottimore and Anne Woolston (Roller) Pyle, and female friends and relatives, chiefly discussing family and social activities. Includes letters, 1910-1911, from Doria S[?] concerning the Camp Fire Girls.
    Burkhardt, Elizabeth Melville
    Calloway, Patricia
    Darley, Albert Roller
    Dunn, Emmett
    Edmonds, Campbell
    Ellis, Nannie P.
    [Gatewood], Margaret
    Gibson, [?]
    Herring, [?]
    Jackson, John L.
    Levy, Helen M.
    Robinson, Evelyn
    Roller, Sara
    S[?], Doria
    Stephenson, Susan C.
    Times-Dispatch, Richmond, Va.
    Virginia. State library, Richmond, Va.
  - Miscellaneous materials, 4 items (Box 29)
    Include account, 1937, with Sydnor & Hundley, Inc., Richmond, Va.; calling card bearing the Cabell coat of arms; newspaper clipping, n.d., announcing Lucy Cabell Roller's election as Commissioner of Girl Scouts in Richmond, Va.; and appraisal of personal property of the estate of Lucy C. Roller, Richmond, Va., 1949.
- Elizabeth Henry (Roller) Bottimore (1902-1993) papers, 1927-1960
  - Correspondence, 1927-1960, 133 items (Box 30-31)
    Correspondence of Elizabeth Henry (Roller) Bottimore of Richmond, Va., and Glens Falls, N.Y., chiefly with female friends and relatives concerning social activities, political events, etc. Prominent correspondents include her mother-in-law, Mrs. John S. Bottimore (of Tazewell, Va.), aunt Annie Cabell (Roller) Flowers (of Inglewood, Nelson co., Va.), half-sister Frances Lewis (Roller) Grattan (of Harrisonburg, Va.), aunt Margaret Etta "Ettie" (Cabell) Matthews (while living in Arrington, Va.), sister Anne Woolston (Roller) Pyle (of Richmond, Va.), sister Lucy Cabell Roller (of Richmond, Va.), niece Lucy Cabell (Pyle) Sommerell (of Richmond, Va., and while attending Wellesley College, Wellesley, Mass., and on a European tour), and Edna Turpin.
    Bessie [?]
    Bobby & Leo [?]
    Bruchie [?]
    Eleanor [?]
    Eloise [?]
    Elsa [?]
    Emily [?]
    Diane [?]
    Gertrude [?]
    Johns [?]
    Lucy [?]
    Rosa [?]
    Anderson, Charles (Mrs.)
    Archer, William W. (Mrs.)
    Battey, Dorothy Dewing
    Belk, Kathleen (Cabell)
    Bott, Bettie Cabell
    Bottimore, John S.
    Cabell, Charles
    Cabell, James Branch
    Cabell, Sallie
    Cassell, Emma (Plecker)
    Clay, Eddie
    Carnahan, Katherine
    Chu, Grace
    Conrad, Edward S. (Mrs.)
    Copping, Allan B.
    Danzell, Francis S. (Mrs.)
    Darley, Alberta Roller
    Edmunds, Patsy
    Freeman, Douglas Southall
    Grattan, George Gilmer, III
    Halliburton, Richard
    Hard, Walter
    Haskell, Alex C.
    [Henry], Rebecca
    Herring, Hildegarde
    Herring, K. G.
    Hook, Clarke W.
    Johnson, Pattie
    Keddy, [Latice]
    Lake, Helen [Bottimore]
    McLandress, Smith
    March, Bob
    Matthews, Hazel
    Mitchell, S. C. (Mrs.)
    P[?], Mary
    Parkinson, Betsy
    Poulen, Tina & Jim
    [Pyle], Anne R[oller]
    [Pyle], Howard
    S[?], M. M.
    S[?], Nonnie M.
    Sadler, Helen
    Shahuck, Rose
    Somerville, Lila
    Sommerell, Lucy Cabell (Pyle)
    [Tidman], P.
    Troubetzkoy, [?]
    Van Laer, Eleanor
    Walcott, Sarah
    Warnen, James M., III
    Willis, L. Mary
    First and Merchants National Bank, Richmond, Va.
    Johnston's Linens, Medin, N.Y.
    Loewner Granite & Marble Co., Inc.
    St. Paul's Church, Richmond, Va.
    Virginia. State Library, Richmond
    Box 30: A - H
    Box 31: J - end
  - Financial materials, 1955, n.d., 33 items (Box 32)
    Include list of personal property belonging to the estate of Lucy Cabell Roller (1899-1949).
  - Commonplace books, 1942, n.d., 2 v. (Box 32)
    Volume I (1942) contains notes on Christmas gifts and cards, household and gardening tips, [notes for a garden society]. Volume II (n.d.) contains notes on music, religion, canning of vegetables, and interior decorating.
  - Invitations, announcements, etc., 1931-1976, 14 items (Box 32)
    Include announcement for the marriage of Elizabeth Henry Roller and William Gordon Bottimore, 1931; and invitation and program for the marriage of Kathleen Cabell to James Patrick Belk, 1976.
  - Miscellaneous materials, 13 items (Box 32)
    Include Certificate of confirmation, 1916 August 20, Christ Church (Episcopal), Norwood, Va.; certificate of marriage, Elizabeth Henry Roller to William Gordon Bottimore, 1931 February 14, St. Paul's Church (Episcopal), Richmond, Va.; notes, recipes, and Red Cross cards and certificates, ca. 1942.
- Anne Woolston (Roller) Pyle (1904-1977) correspondence, 1912-1959, 12 items (Box 33)
  Scattered correspondence of Anne Woolston (Roller) Pyle including correspondence with camp directors at Green Cove and Mondamin concerning her children, reports from Chatham Episcopal Institute, Chatham, Va., and a letter from Mrs. Margaret S. Rothert, Richmond, Va., enclosing a bank note on the Central Bank of Virginia signed by J. S. Roller.
  Huston, Alice S.
  Pyle, Anne Roller
  Pyle, Howard
  Rothert, Margaret S.
  Chatham Episcopal Institute, Chatham, Va.
  Green Cove Camp
  Mondamin Camp
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1872-1907, 21 items (Box 33)
  Miscellaneous correspondence of various Cabell, Micklem and Roller family members, and others. Chiefly letters to Caroline Elizabeth (Micklem) James while attending school at "Inglewood," Nelson co., Va., including letters from John Willis Cabell, Lettie R. Goodwin, and Margaret Etta (Eubank) Micklem. Also included are letters of Anne Woolston (Cabell) Cabell to Margaret Clifford Cabell and Sallie Laidley Cabell; letter of Ellen B. (Roller) Robertson to Frances Antoinette (Roller) Calwell; and a letter from George S. Gibbs, White Sulphur Springs, W. Va., 1873, to Robert Douglas Roller concerning the gaiety of fellow patrons of the springs. Caroline Elizabeth (Micklem) James correspondence is grouped together. All other correspondence alphabetically by author.
  James, Caroline Elizabeth (Micklem) correspondence
  Miscellaneous correspondence
  Charlotte [?] to Miss Edythe Cornell
  Nettie [?] to Sallie [?]
  Cabell, Anne Woolston (Cabell), to Margaret Clifford Cabell
  Cabell, Anne Woolston (Cabell), to [Sallie Jordan Laidley Cabell]
  Gibbs, George S., to Robert Douglas Roller
  Halsey, Virginia H., to Mrs. W. H. "Anna" Whelan
  [Higginbotham], Lula [Coleman], to Allen [?]
  Higginbotham, Mary Ida (Day), to Mary Frances Coleman Higginbotham and Jessie Woods (Higginbotham) Matthews
  Rialto grain and securities company, St. Louis, Mo., to Willis Milton Eubank
  Robertson, Ellen Booker (Roller), to Frances Antoinette (Roller) Calwell
  S[?], J[?] C[?], to Margaret Etta (Eubank) Micklem
  Surber, Thad, to Michael Bowyer Calwell